You are planning to create a
您打算建立一支
space army armed with ball lightning.
以球状闪电为武器的太空军队
Pity.
可惜
No one survived inside.
里面没有活人
What have you done?
你都做了什么
Did what you wanted.
做了您想做的
I lit the fire
我点燃了火
but I can't control it.
却控制不了它
The fire started to spread
火势开始蔓延了
I did what I could.
我也做了我能做的
It's your turn.
该你们了
PDC Issues Latest Notice on Ladder Accident.
PDC就天梯事故发布最新通报
Ten days ago
十天前
Tianlai high-altitude transfer station located in geosynchronous orbit
位于地球同步轨道的天梯高空中转站
was hit by accident.
遭受意外撞击
Since the accident
事故发生后
the PDC launched an emergency response
PDC启动应急响应
to do everything possible to treat the wounded
全力救治伤者
and stabalize the aftermath.
开展善后工作
It has assessed
经评估
that the impact damaged part of the structure of the ladder
撞击致使天梯部分结构受损
but did not significantly affect the continued construction of the spacedock.
但并未显著影响太空船坞的持续建设
The ladder project has officially resumed.
天梯工程现已正式复工
At the same time, The PDC solemnly expresses
同时PDC郑重表示
that the process of human exploration of the universe is bound to be difficult
人类探索宇宙的过程必然艰辛
but we will overcome.
但我们克服万难
We will never waver in our resolve to advance the mainstream defense initiatives.
推进主流防御计划的决心绝不会动摇
In addition, the rumor that the wallfacer, Mr. Tyler's, plan was exposed has attracted the attention of all parties.
此外面壁者泰勒被破壁的传言引起了各方关注
The specific content of the plan has aroused heated debate among the public.
其计划的具体内容引起民众热议
The PDC convenes an urgent hearing and makes a statement
PDC紧急召开听证会并做出声明
that the Wallfacer Project must not contain any aspects that harms human life
面壁计划绝不能存在伤害人类生命的内容
and therefore disagrees with Mr. Tyler.
因此针对泰勒先生的
The newly built space elevator is badly damaged.
新建成的太空电梯破坏严重
ThehHigh-altitude transfer station structure is torn.
高空中转站结构撕裂
The spacedock is over 90% destroyed.
太空船坞损毁超过90%
Massive debris caused 132 satellites to be scrapped.
大量碎片导致132架卫星报废
And within 5 years will collide with the space station.
并在5年内都将对空间站
This also poses a thread to spacecraft and outer space activities.
航天器和外空活动构成威胁
The cleanup of debris is in progress.
碎片清理正在进行
The overall progress of mainstream defense plans
主流防御计划整体进度
has been delayed by about 18 months.
推迟约18个月
In the accident
事故中
a total of 271 people died on the spot.
共计271人当场死亡
272 people.
272人
Subsequent impact is still being counted
后续影响尚在统计
It is clear
很明显
That this is a terrorist attack against the Wallfacer project.
这是一次针对面壁计划的恐怖袭击
The ETO agent codenamed "Von Neumann"
代号“冯・诺伊曼”的ETO残党
must take full responsibility for the accident.
必须为这次事故负全部责任
No.
不
What he said is true.
他说的都是真的
He fabricated remarks
他捏造的破壁言论
that fellow human beings will not believe.
所有人类同胞都不会相信
In the name of the Wallfacers, we have
我们已经以面壁者的名义
properly accommodated the families of the victims.
妥善安置了罹难者家属
Soon after, the ladder
天梯不久后
will also be fully repaired.
也会完全修复
The war has just begun.
战争才刚刚开始
Humanity needs you
人类需要你
Mr. Tyler.
泰勒先生
My mission is over
我的使命结束了
madam president.
萨伊主席
As I have said in the hearing
听证会上我已经说了
I have resigned from Wallfacer duties
我解除面壁者的职务
and please
并且申请
make my statement available to the world.
向全球公开我的声明
I can.
可以
Mr. Tyler
泰勒先生
have you heard the story of Abraham?
你听过亚伯拉罕的故事吗
The part on Mount Moriah.
摩利亚地山上的那段
We can only choose whether to sacrifice
我们只能选择是否牺牲
but we can't choose what to sacrifice.
但不能选择牺牲什么
This is what you've been looking for
这也是你一直想找的东西
Mr. Tyler.
泰勒先生
How do you respond to the wallbreaker's statement
您如何回应破壁人的陈述
Did you deliberately design the failure of the two experiments?
两次实验失败是您故意设计的吗
Is it to deceive Tomoko?
是为了蒙蔽智子吗
Is the wallbreaker part of your plan?
被破壁也是您计划的一部分吗
Do you feel like you successfully cheated the ETO?
您觉得自己成功欺骗了ETO吗
What do you expect the ETO to do next?
您预计ETO还会有什么动作
Do you think there will be new wallbreakers?
您觉得还会出现新的破壁人吗
Can you publicly refute the wallbreakers statement?
您能公开反驳破壁人的言论吗
What do you want to say to the ETO agents?
您有什么想对ETO残党说的
Is Wallbreaker von Neumann still alive?
破壁人冯・诺伊曼还活着吗
After meeting the wallbreaker for the first time
首次遭遇破壁人后
what advice do you have for other wallfacers?
您有什么经验分享给其他面壁者
We believe in wallfacer Tyler.
我们相信面壁者泰勒
Mr. Tyler.
泰勒先生
Where will you choose for your next experimental site?
您下一次的实验场地选在哪
What is your next plan?
您的下一步计划是什么
Long Live the Wallfacer Project.
这次太空实验失败导致的惨重损失
Is Dr. Elena responsible?
是您手下的埃琳娜博士负全责吗
Brother Luo.
罗老弟
Someone is looking for you.
有人找
Who?
谁啊
I'll return soon, wait for me.
那你等我一下 很快
Go ahead.
你先去吧
I will just go tidy up my room.
我正好上房间收拾一下
It's so beautiful here.
这里真美啊
Like heaven.
就像天堂
Yes.
是啊
That's all I want.
这就是我的全部
I'm terribly sorry.
很抱歉
We're fine.
我们没事
It's in the past.
过去的
Don't mention it.
就不提了
You are a smart man.
你是个聪明人
From a certain point of view
甚至从某种角度来说
you are even the most responsible.
你才是那个最具有责任感的人
Me?
我
How can that be?
怎么可能
At least
至少
you never hurt
你没有伤害过
the people who should be protected.
本应该保护的人
You are right
你是对的
I came to you
我来找你
because only we can understand each other's pain.
是因为只有我们能理解对方的痛苦
That person..
那个人
is it true?
说的是真的吗
He guessed right.
他猜对了
But it wasn't this that hit me the hardest.
但对我打击最大的不是这个
After the wallbreaker appeared
破壁人出现后
the wallbreaker website made all my plans public.
破壁网站就公开了我的所有计划
The PDC also prepared to sentence me for crimes against humanity
PDC也准备以反人类罪裁决我
but they said
结果他们却说
the evidence
这些证据
may be part of my strategy.
可能是我战略的一部分
I will not charged.
我不受指控
Everybody gave me that smile
所有人都对我露出那种微笑
and declared the meeting closed.
宣布会议结束
I was completely devastated.
我当时完全崩溃了
I rushed out of the venue.
我冲出会场
Yelled at people in the square.
向广场的人大叫
I'm wallfacer Tyler.
我是面壁者泰勒
My wallbreaker
我的破壁人
successfully revealed my strategy.
成功地揭穿了我的战略
He is right.
他是对的
I'm going to use ball lightning
我要用球状闪电
to attack the earth fleet.
去攻击地球舰队
I want them to fight as quantum ghosts.
我要让他们作为量子幽灵去作战
I'm going to kill, I'm against humanity.
我要杀人我反人类
Kill me, punish me.
杀了我吧你们惩罚我吧
The only result of this..
结果呢
A large group of people gathered around me in the square to watch.
广场上一大群人围着我看
Their eyes seem to say
他们的眼神像是在说
Look.
看啊
He is a wallfacer.
他是面壁者
He is still working.
他在工作
How well he did.
他做得多好
How much you pretend.
装得多像
Breaker?
破壁人
How can we see through his real purpose?
怎么能识破他的真实目的呢
You laughed too..
你也笑了
The smile of a wallfacer.
对面壁者的笑
A wallfacer laughs at another wallfacer.
一个面壁者对另一个面壁者的笑
You also think I'm working.
你也觉得我是在工作
a disguise..
在伪装
Still executing the plan, right?
还在执行计划是吧
How did we get put in such a ridiculous situation?
我们怎么会被置于如此滑稽的境地
Mr. Tyler
泰勒先生
This..
这个
I'm afraid it's a vicious cycle that we'll never escape.
恐怕是我们永远没法脱身的怪圈
I tried.
我试过了
never escape..
永远没法脱身
No.
不
There is a way.
有办法的
I'm here to tell you how.
我就是来告诉你这个办法的
You need rest.
你需要休息
Rest here for a few days.
在这里好好休息几天吧
I need to rest.
我需要休息
Can I stay here for a while?
我可以在这待一会吗
You can do anything
你在这儿
while you are here.
可以做任何想做的事
Relax
好好放松一下吧
for a while.
一会儿
Join us for dinner.
我叫你吃饭
Brother Luo.
罗老弟
Are you OK?
你没事吧
No way.
不会吧
We gather here
我们聚集在这里
for wallfacer
是为面壁者
Frederick Tyler's daughter.
弗里德里克-泰勒的女儿
The death of Dr. Elena.
埃琳娜博士的殉职
I offer my deepest condolences.
献上最深切的哀思
Greetings to my fellow human beings.
敬告各位人类同胞
From human history to the present day
自人类历史延绵至今
we have experienced countless catastrophes.
经历过无数巨大的灾难
We have survived plague and war
我们从瘟疫和战乱中幸存下来
and in the oceans
并在海洋
deserts and plains
沙漠和平原中
we built an immortal civilization.
建立了不朽的文明
It was a rocky but glorious 3 million years
这坎坷但辉煌的300万年
but on a cosmic scale
在宇宙尺度下
this is merely a moment.
或许只算是一瞬间
No race
但没有任何种族
or any civilization
任何文明
can for any reason big
能够以任何理由
or small, obliterate everything we hold dear.
小 和抹杀我们珍视的一切
so
所以
at the moment we are going to discuss
此刻我们要讨论的
not just survival
不只是生存
but dignity.
更是尊严
The enemy is present.
大敌当前
The wallfacer plan and mainstream defense plan will cooperate with each other
面壁计划和主流防御计划互相配合
and take advantage of each.
各取所长
This is a testament to the cohesion and vitality of human beings.
这正是人类凝聚力和生命力的铁证
Now
如今
the Wallfacer Project enters a period of submersion.
面壁计划进入沉潜时期
Under the threat of the ETO organization
在ETO组织的反扑下
humanities defenses are being eaten away.
人类的防御正在被蚕食
The willpower of humanity
人类的信念
accepts the challenge.
正在接受挑战
We are not afraid of the challenge
但我们不惧挑战
because human being are between life and death.
因为人类在生死存亡之际
We are not only individuals,
绝不是一盘散沙
but an indestructible whole.
而是坚不可摧的整体
In the darkest hour
越是至暗时刻
we must gather the trust of all mankind.
越要凝聚全人类的信任
I firmly believe this time
我坚信这一次
Humanity will win.
人类必胜
The wallfacer's sleep is not the wallfacer's end.
面壁者的沉睡不是面壁计划的沉睡
We will rebuild the ladder.
天梯的重建
It symbolizes that we can conquer all obstacles.
则象征我们能征服一切险阻
If mainstream defense plans were humanity's shield.
如果主流防御计划是人类的盾牌
Then wallfacers
那么面壁计划
in our minds,
则是以我们的思维
are a sharp sword pointed at Trisolaran's throat.
指向三体人咽喉的一把利剑
As the current chairman of the PDC
作为PDC现任主席
I will take the survival of mankind as the highest mission
我将以人类存续为最高使命
at any cost to
不惜一切代价
protect our home planet from being violated.
守护我们的母星不被侵犯
I will lead you
将带领你们
to win this war.
打赢这一场战争
Let the approaching invaders see
更要让正在逼近的侵略者看到
human beings may be small
人类或许渺小
but we never give in.
但永不屈服
If this is the last view..
如果这是最后的景色了
Not bad.
倒也不错
Right?
对吗
But you don't want to know.
但你不想知道
Ladder
天梯
What happened.
到底发生了什么吗
Chairman.
主席
How is the damage?
受损情况怎么样
Ball lightning breaks down the boundary between macro and micro
球状闪电击穿了宏观和微观的界限
This is impossible.
这不可能
Innumerable possibilities superimposed.
无数的可能性叠加在一起
What emerges is entirely determined by probability.
呈现出什么完全由概率决定
This issue.
这事
Come out evil.
得出邪招
Them..
他们
what will happen?
到底会怎么样
Don't look back.
别回头
I can only say
我只能说
like Schrödinger's cat that is both alive and dead.
像薛定谓那只既生又死的猫
Are we underestimating the complexity of the disaster?
我们是不是低估了灾难的复杂程度
This is the true face of the universe.
这才是宇宙的真面目
Everything is uncertain.
一切不确定
At a fundamental level.
都被过滤掉了
It is only numbers.
只看得到数字
Coordinate System.
坐标系
So you're saying
所以你是说
the real disaster has just begun.
真正的灾难才刚开始